It is קכ"ד Kuf Chaf Dalet 124 and
we pick up on the bottom of קכ"ג עמוד ב' Kuf Chaf
Gimmel Amud Bet
and let's see where we are exactly.
Okay,
so where are we?
I'm sorry, right. Okay, מותיב רבי ירמיה. Masiv Rabbi Yirmiya. The line
starts with the word רבי ירמיה. Rabbi Yirmiya. It is about 13
lines from the bottom. So מותיב רבי ירמיה, Masiv Rabbi Yirmiya, Rabbi
Yirmiya asked.
We're dealing with the question about there was a statement that if
you tear a garment, once it's majority torn, it's no longer considered
a garment and even if it was טמא tamei it becomes טהור.
tahor. And then there were qualifications. Some said this was only true
if this was we have to make in general a גזירה דרבנן
gezeira d'rabbanan and it was only true in very unique circumstances. Others
said that it was only true for and now we're dealing with
רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's statement and ריש לקיש's Resh Lakish's statement that
says it's only true for cloth, but for leather because leather is
strong, even the majority torn would not be an issue. So within
that we are going this is the position that is currently being
challenged. So let's take a look.
So מותיב רבי ירמיה, Masiv Rabbi Yirmiya, המפשיט בבהמה ובחיה בטהורה ובטמאה
בדקה ובגסה, Hamaphshit b'vehema u'v'chaya b'tehora u'v'tmeia b'daka u'v'gasa, so our entire
משנה, Mishna, somebody who is flaying an animal, all different types of
animals, לשטיח l'shatiach if you're making it for a mat, then it
is כדי אחיזה. k'dei achiza. Then as soon as you remove the
amount of grasping, then the skin that is already flayed off is
no longer considered connected, you know, even though it's all one piece,
but the flayed part is not connected. So the גמרא Gemara says,
היתר מכדי אחיזה טהור. Hayeter mik'dei achiza tahor. Once you get beyond
that amount of כדי אחיזה, k'dei achiza, as I just said, the
flayed skin is not connected. ואמאי, V'amai, why is that true? לימא
חלים, Lima cholim, why don't we say that leather is strong and
therefore it's still considered connected? Now תוספות Tosafot is very bothered by
this comparison. What is the analogy? asks תוספות. Tosafot. Once you tear
a garment and you say if the leather garment, the bottom part
is still considered strong so it still retains its sort of integrity
even with a tear, is very different than, you know, if you're
flaying off a piece of skin that since part of the skin
is connected, what, you're going to say that the flayed skin is
also connected to the meat? It's like very different than if you
have a piece of leather with a tear in it as opposed
to removing skin, even though it'll eventually be leather, from meat. So
תוספות Tosafot really, you know, is I mean he tries to explain
what the analogy is, but in the end it really is a
challenging analogy here. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara somehow says if we're saying
this concept that it's strong, then then maybe even the flayed skin
should be considered connected. So תרגמה רבי אבין ראשון ראשון נפל. Targama
Rabbi Avin rishon rishon nepal. No, here it's different. As every little
bit that you flay off, it's like it's already disconnected. So, you
know, it's a little bit begs the question, but the point seems
to be that it's different than the case of the garment. The
garment you're tearing a garment and as long as it's strong on
the bottom maybe it's connected. Here you're removing something from the skin,
so every bit you remove is like it's already fallen off. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara goes on, מותיב רבי יוסף. Masiv Rabbi
Yosef. So another similar comparison to skin that's being flayed to tearing
a leather garment. עור של צואר רבי יוחנן בן נורי אומר אינו
חיבור. Or shel tzavar Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri omer eino chibur. That
when you get to the neck, if you're flaying an animal from
the feet to the head and you get to the neck, is
the skin left on the neck still considered connected even though it
has not been flayed yet? So רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri says it is not. So the גמרא Gemara says אמאי
חלים, Amai cholim, how could that be? Now this maybe comparison is
a little bit better. If leather is strong, so at least certainly
the part of the skin that's still connected to the flesh should
still be considered one unit even if the rest has been removed.
חלים וקאי. Cholim v'kai. So אמר ליה אביי אימא סיפא. Amar lei
Abaye eima seifa. So why are you asking from רבי אבין, Rabbi
Avin, how about ask from the end of the משנה? Mishna? וחכמים
אומרים חיבור. V'chachamim omrim chibur. It is still considered to the connected
to the neck. So that supports the position of ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish that leather is strong. אלא אמר אביי. Ela amar Abaye. So
אביי Abaye said don't bother us with this משנה. Mishna. This is
not related to ריש לקיש's Resh Lakish's case of tearing a leather
garment. Here we're talking about בשומר העשוי לנתק מאליו קמיפלגי. B'shomer ha'asui
l'natek me'elav kamifligi. Here we're talking about a שומר, shomer, right, that
is the idea of the skin connected to the meat. It's a
שומר shomer to the meat, but it is going to fall off
on its own accord. It's going to naturally fall off even without
you continuing the job. Once you've removed everything up to the neck,
you have flayed the animal from the feet all the way to
the neck, so even if you don't continue the flaying, naturally with
all that skin removed, it's just going to somehow fall off, you
know, naturally on its own. Yeah, or right, gravity takes hold or
something. Okay. So anyway, so here the point is it's a little
bit ironic, right, or whatever, it's interesting. The משנה, Mishna, the beginning
of the משנה Mishna is even stuff that you have removed from
the skin, because it's very close to the skin and hard to
remove the leather from the skin, even the leather that's already been
flayed if it's one piece, it's still considered connected. The end of
the משנה Mishna is the opposite. Even stuff that's still connected, if
it's going to fall off by itself, might be considered disconnected. So
that's the issue by the skin of the neck. מר סבר הוה
שומר, Mar savar hava shomer, it still is a שומר shomer because
right now it still is connected. ומר סבר לא הוה שומר, U-mar
savar lo hava shomer, it's not a שומר. shomer. אמר
מותיב רבי ירמיה, Amar motiv Rabbi Yirmiya, so now Rabbi Yirmiya asks,
so that's a nice way incidentally we've now explained the debate at
the end of the משנה. Mishna. But now we're still with this
whole idea of ריש לקיש Resh Lakish and whether leather preserves the
integrity at the bottom of the garment. תנור שנטמא כיצד מטהרין אותו.
Tanur she-nitma keitzad metaherin oto. Now we are going to make if
the analogy that analogy was funny, that analogy was keeping it in
the same material, leather or skin which can become leather, but very
different scenarios: rending a leather garment and flaying skin from an animal.
Now we're going to have similar scenarios: rending of a vessel, breaking
a vessel, but we're going to compare very different materials. If you're
going to say leather is strong and preserves the integrity, now we're
going to ask about a case of a pottery vessel that you're
breaking and that maybe there even if part of it is broken
we should say pottery is strong so the integrity is preserved even
when some of it is broken if that's the argument you make
by leather. And we're going to look at the ovens. Now the
ovens that they had in the time of חז"ל Chazal basically were
like sort of like huge pots, תנור, tanur, you know, but they
were like a big pottery pot and it was connected to the
ground. They would sort of make it separately and then plaster it
to the ground. But because this was, you know, originally made separately,
although some things that are connected to the ground under some circumstances
can't become טמא, tamei, this could become טמא. tamei. I mean the
תורה Torah talks about a pottery תנור tanur becoming טמא. tamei. תנור
וכירים יותץ טמאים הם, Tanur ve-khirayim yutatz tme'im hem, right, they have
to be shattered. So here is משניות Mishnayot in כלים Keilim that
deal with this issue about a pottery vessel, here a whole oven,
that became טמא tamei and you have to break it. How much
when you break it does it lose its integrity as a vessel?
Similar to the tearing of the טלית, tallit, of the garment, when
it stops being the vessel then it loses its identity and can
become
טהור. tahor. If it's pottery? Yeah.
Well it is true. It's connected. Yes. Well they put or
they put other vessels in it.
Oh they put other they put other vessels in it, right, right.
They built the they built the there were like holes at the
bottom or something, I forget the different types, there's a תנור וכירים,
tanur ve-khirayim, I mean they actually have they actually have it
was a clay oven.
It was a clay oven, right, and you had you had fire
on the bottom and you put pots exactly on the hole on
top, exactly, exactly. Okay, so תנור שנטמא כיצד מטהרין אותו, Tanur she-nitma
keitzad metaherin oto, so if an oven becomes טמא tamei how do
you purify it? By breaking it. חלקו לשלושה, Chalko li-shlosha, you break
it into three parts, because if you broke it into two parts,
one part would be the larger part and would be the majority.
So if there's a majority, that majority is
still טמא, tamei, still retains its identity. Okay, but if you break
it into three parts, no part is the majority so it loses
its identity. וגורר את הטפילה, Ve-gorer et ha-tpila, you remove the plaster
at the bottom that is keeping it connected to the ground, עד
שיהא בארץ, ad she-yehei ba-aretz, until you get it to the ground,
which means either you remove all the plaster till you reach the
ground, you remove all the plaster so the so the oven sits
on the ground, basically you remove all the plaster. רבי
מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir omer, אינו צריך לא לגרור את הטפילה ולא
עד שיהא בארץ, eino tzarikh lo ligror et ha-tpila velo ad she-yehei
ba-aretz, you don't have to do that, remove the plaster or bring
it to the ground, אלא ממעטו מבפנים מארבעה
טפחים. ela mem'ato mi-bifnim me-arba'a tfachim. The plaster's on the outside, so
don't worry about the plaster on the outside, just make it smaller
מבפנים, mi-bifnim, it's funny because if you're going to break it you
think you'd break something working on the outside in, but the point
is you don't have to worry about removing the outer plaster, you
just break you just, you know, cut it in half or whatever
you cut it down so that you're only left with ארבעה טפחים
arba'a tfachim of of the oven. Okay, any oven less than ארבעה
טפחים arba'a tfachim according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir doesn't have a
status of an oven. A minimum size of an oven is ארבעה
טפחים, arba'a tfachim, so once you get it beyond lower than ארבעה
טפחים arba'a tfachim you're fine.
Measure from the outside?
Oh that's an interesting point, maybe that's what he means מבפנים, mi-bifnim,
that you measure the ארבעה טפחים arba'a tfachim from the inside. Meaning
if the oven is a טפח tefach removed from the ground, that
might be that's a good point about why he might say מבפנים,
mi-bifnim, you're measuring right the actual sort of vessel itself, so you're
measuring it from the inside, not from its height from the ground.
It did not have a bottom? It did not have a top,
correct. It had fire on the bottom, it was open on the
top and you just sort of suspend pots from the rim around
it. Okay. What? Like a grill, right. Except that you would lower
stuff into it, it would not just be on the top of
it, right. Okay. אוקיי, כי ממעט ליה מארבעה מאי הוי? Okay, ki
mem'at leh me-arba'a mai havai? The גמרא Gemara says
but look, nevertheless according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, it's sufficient that
you get it less than four. אמאי? Amai? Why? לימא החלים וקאי?
Leima hachalim ve-ka'i?
It's strong and retains its integrity. Meaning if you're saying when you
rend a leather garment, if it's, you know, that because there's some
stuff left at the bottom it retains its integrity, so here too
even if you break an oven, if there's, you know, four if
there's stuff pottery is, you know, clay is strong, so it should
retain its integrity. Now again the comparison is bizarre, besides just comparing
leather to pottery, there you could say the גמרא Gemara understands that
they're similar in their qualities of sort of of being strong. So
here too, even if you break an oven, if there's, if there's
stuff, if pottery is strong, so it should retain its integrity. Now
again, the comparison is bizarre besides just comparing leather to pottery. There
you could say the גמרא Gemara understands that they're similar in their
qualities of sort of being strong as material. But when you rend
a leather garment, you still have the whole garment connected at the
bottom. Like the whole point is you haven't torn it the whole
way. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is saying if there's a leather, if
there's some stuff left at the bottom and it's leather, it's still
considered to be one unit. But here you've actually broken the pottery
off. So who cares if you've got a strong bottom, right? It
doesn't connect to the other stuff in any way. So again, some
of these comparisons are very hard to understand. Anyway, let's see what
the גמרא's Gemara answer is. אמר רבא ואימא מדרבנן, Amar Rava ve-eima
mid-rabbanan, why are you asking from רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says
that less than ארבעה טפחים arba tefachim is still,
it makes it טהור, tahor, ask from the Rabbis. וגורר את הטפל
עד כי בארץ, ve-go-er et ha-tefel ad ki-ba'aretz, that
the Rabbis say you have to totally break break it. So you
see that's consistent with ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, because it's a strong
material, you would have to completely break it in order for it
to be טהור. tahor. אלא אמר רבא הכי קאמר, Ella amar Rava
hachi ka-amar, so here's really what the debate is between the Rabbis
and רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
They're really not debating how you make it טהור. tahor. Everybody would
agree that when it comes to making it טהור tahor based on
ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish idea, because it's a strong material, you have
to totally break it. תנור שנטמא כיצד מטהרין אותו, Tannur she-nitma keitzad
meta-harin oto, how do you make it טהור? tahor? דברי הכל חולקו
לשלושה וגורר את הטפל עד שיבא בארץ, Divrei hakol cho-leko li-shlosha ve-gorers
et ha-tefel ad she-yavo ba'aretz, you have to break it into three
and get it down to the ground and remove the plaster. Based
on, informed by ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish idea that what do you
call it, that if it's a strong material it has to be
completely rendered, rended I guess I should say. Now, הרוצה שלא יבא
תנור לידי טומאה, ha-rotzeh she-lo yavo tannur li-yedei tumah, if
however it's not טמא, tamei, you don't have to break it to
make it טהור, tahor, you want to construct an oven so it
never becomes טמא, tamei, it never has a status of an oven,
so from the very beginning you're making it in a way that
it's not recognized as an oven, כיצד הוא עושה, Keitzad hu oseh,
what can you do? So the Rabbis would say, חולקו לשלושה וגורר
את הטפל עד שיבא בארץ. cho-leko li-shlosha ve-gorers et ha-tefel ad she-yavo
ba'aretz. So you could break it. Now of course, how you're going
to use something that's broken and not connected to the ground, maybe
I don't know what it means. Maybe it means like you know
that you're about to bring a מת meis into the house and
you want to stop your oven from being טמא. tamei. So is
there a way you can now, right, because you'll fix it afterwards,
you'll fix it afterwards. Is there a way that if you preempt
the situation, it can be better than having to solve it after
the problem? So the חכמים chachamim say no different. Right, doesn't matter
whether you're trying to preempt or not, you're going to have to
break your oven completely. But רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, oh, ran out
of battery? I don't know. Okay, whatever. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says,
all right, whatever. רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir omer, says that there
is a way.
What, so רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that it is different if
you try to if you try to preempt it. רבי מאיר אומר
אין צריך לא לגרור את הטפל ולא עד שיבא בארץ אלא ממעטו
מבפנים מארבעה טפחים. Rabbi Meir omer ein tzarich lo-ligror et ha-tefel velo
ad she-yavo ba'aretz ella mima'ato mibifnim me-arba tefachim. No,
if you're preempting it, it's enough that it's smaller than ארבעה טפחים,
arba tefachim, because then it never has a status of an oven.
So anyway, what we have done is well we're going to talk
about that, but apparently no real oven was that small. No oven
that was considered usable less than that size. So basically what,
right, which is pretty interesting, the idea that, you know, you could
put other stuff in it, you could put like, you know, you
could store apples in it. So and normally but actually,
you know, right, what you see here is that if it's not
functional for the purpose for which it's made, I mean that's a
whole, you know, that's why there's thirty chapters of מסכת כלים maseches
keilim because how you measure something about like what its original status
is and when it breaks, what status it can, what function it
can now play, what was the intention of the function that it
was supposed to be playing. But yes, what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
is implicitly saying here is if its purpose is to function as
an oven and it's not able to function as such, it's not
recognized as a כלי kli at all, which is definitely a surprising
idea. But that's what you have for רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. But
what we've managed to do is we've managed to say if it
became טמא, tamei, we've relegated their debate to the initial ability for
it to become טמא. tamei. But if it became טמא, tamei, in
order to make it טהור, tahor, everybody would agree you have to
totally break it, and that's because of following ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish
idea, or reshaping the debate based on ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish idea,
that if it's a strong material then you have to completely break
it. Okay, so that's that. But now the גמרא Gemara is not
done. The גמרא Gemara says like the גמרא Gemara wants to figure
out if this, you know, how these positions really make sense. So
let's take a look. אמר מר חולקו לשלושה, Amar mar cho-leko li-shlosha,
so you're telling me that according to the חכמים chachamim you have
to break it in three. Now, if רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
it's enough to get it down to less than ארבעה, arba, okay,
that means that when the חכמים chachamim say you have to break
it in three, they're saying breaking it in two wouldn't work, even
though presumably it would be a case where breaking it in two,
if they're debating רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
once it's less than ארבעה arba you're okay. So if the חכמים
chachamim are saying breaking it in two doesn't work, presumably that's even
if when you broke it in two,
each piece was less than ארבעה טפחים, arba tefachim, right? They're saying
that doesn't work, but רבי Rabbi says no, it's actually fine as
long as it's less than ארבעה. arba. So from the חכמים chachamim
it's implicit in the חכמים chachamim that they disagree with רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, forget that, that they disagree with רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir saying you have to
get
less than ארבעה arba suffice. Okay, so we're going to challenge that
question whether the rabbis really disagree with רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir that
less than four suffices. Let's take a look. תנור שתחילתו ארבעה ושיורו
ארבעה. Tannur she-techilato arba ve-shiyaro arba. This is an earlier משנה Mishnah
in כלים. Kelim. A תנור tannur begins its initial size to be
considered an oven, like רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir just said, to be
considered really having a status of an oven and being able to
become טמא, tamei, to be the vessel it was made for, has
to be at least four טפחים. tefachim. And when it was if
it was larger and broken, for it to still have a status
of an oven, also it goes by four טפחים. tefachim. This is
what רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says. I should say parenthetically that the
simple sense of this משנה Mishnah is exactly against what רבא Rava
said before. The simple sense of this משנה Mishnah sees that רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir says that even if it became טמא, tamei, in
order to make it טהור tahor it's enough that you get it
below four. That's what שיורו ארבעה shiyaro arba means, that if it
started bigger and it's now less left at less than four, it
no longer has the status of an oven. But anyway, presumably רבא
Rava would say what that means would be all of that is
before it became טמא. tamei. If it started bigger, you get it
less than four. Anyway, that's what רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says. An
oven when you make it initially has to have four טפחים tefachim
to be considered an oven and if it was made bigger and
it broke, then it's also stops being an oven when it's less
than four טפחים. tefachim. That's what רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says.
Okay, so שיורו ארבעה shiyaro arba I mean if
it started larger and you broke it. It's still an oven as
long as it has four טפחים, tefachim, but less than four טפחים
tefachim it's not. וחכמים אומרים, Ve-chachamim omrim, the sages say, במה דברים
אמורים? בגדול. אבל בקטן, תחילתו כל שהוא. be-meh devarim amurim? Bi-gadol. Aval
be-katan, techilato kol she-hu.
When is that true? If it's a large oven. Large oven, you
know, you're making it for normal kitchen use, you're right, it goes
by the size of four טפחים. tefachim. אבל בקטן, Aval be-katan, a
small oven, which is I guess what, you know, Rivka was asking,
תחילתו כל שהוא משתיגמר מלאכתו. techilato kol she-hu mi-she-tigamer melachto.
Even if the smallest thing or you know, if you're having it
to do some function, you know, maybe you want to use it
for I don't know, making sauces or something, so who needs four
טפחים? tefachim? If you're having it to do some function, whatever size
you made it, that counts. Okay, ושיורו דרובו. ve-shiyaro de-rubo.
And if it broke, then you can't measure it by four טפחים,
tefachim, so you would say it retains its status as long as
it's its majority.
Now רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir doesn't care how big it initially...
well, we're going to talk about that in a minute. וכמה כל
שהוא? Ve-kamma kol she-hu? You gotta love the גמרא, Gemara, right? Even
the smallest amount. Okay, but how big? וכמה כל שהוא? Ve-kamma kol
she-hu? What's the size? What's the size of... you don't really mean
it! So אמרי דבי רבי ינאי, amrei de-vei Rebbi Yannai, טפח. tefach.
Okay, we know what we mean, at least even as small as
a טפח, tefach, right? Like four, three inches or so. Now what
do you use an oven that small for?
I said maybe for sauces or something. So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. Remember by the way, you could use a pot
that small, but we're talking not about the pot, but about the
oven. The idea is you put a fire in it, you put
a pot inside of it. What are you going to do with
something that's just a טפח? tefach? So the גמרא Gemara says, so
שכן עושין תנורים בנות טפח. she-ken osin tannurim benot tefach.
You make like play ovens the size of a טפח. tefach. You
see, somebody play school, who makes those plastic like play kitchens? What?
Fisher-Price. Oh, they also...
oh, like a sample.
Yeah, I know what you mean.
Those were the Easy-Bake ovens. Oh,
right.
So anyway, so they had them in the time of the גמרא,
Gemara, they made little play ovens. So that they make the... a
sample. Okay, maybe a sample.
Those were actually used.
Right. Used for for kids who are playing house.
They don't actually put anything in there.
I don't know, not clear.
Even though you can't actually really cook anything in them, you know,
presumably you wouldn't let your kid with a live fire.
Right. Right. But you could heat up water. But that's not what
the גמרא Gemara is saying. At least the way רש"י Rashi understands
it. רש"י Rashi understands the word בנות benot here probably is referring
to the oven. The oven is the size of a טפח. tefach.
That's what בנות טפח benot tefach means. But רש"י, Rashi, yeah, רש"י
Rashi says, it's not clear to me how רש"י Rashi is reading
the word בנות, benot, because רש"י Rashi actually says לתינוקות. le-tinokot. So
an egg oven.
Even though it's not actually usable, or is it?
Well, that's the point, you know, that sort of goes to Dov's
question, which is if it's if it's good for the purpose for
which it was made, right? So then it is, and pottery, you
know, כלי חרס klei cheres has to have a תוך, toch, obviously,
because it's only מיטמא מתוכו. mitamei mi-tocho. But you know, maybe the
kid puts little play food in it and a play fire in
it, but apparently that's okay as long as it's good for the
purpose it's made. If it's made to serve as a real oven,
you could say even though, you know, we can have objective standards
that that's not a real oven, it's so big. But if it's
made as a play oven, then play ovens have a different size
and as long as it's functional for that purpose, presumably, yeah, exactly,
exactly, exactly. A small share...
that's a good question. Yes, but then
when you break it into three, yeah, why don't you say that
the first time you break it, the larger piece is still the
oven, and then the second time you break it, the larger of
those two pieces is still...
that is a good question. First of all, you could do one
act of breaking and it breaks into three pieces, so it's not
two stages. But the other point is that the larger piece has
the טומאה tumah of an oven, but I'm not sure we would
still call it an oven if it's not functional as such. Right.
But that's interesting. That's an interesting... you know, it goes into... of
all of these issues about exactly that question. I mean, actually, on
the previous דף daf there was a huge רשי Rashi that was
discussing all these questions about how do you measure something as a
vessel and do you use different standards in terms of size and
minimum sizes etc. sort of when it's initially in terms of its
initial identity as opposed to when it actually is broken, there the
size of how you measure something as still having some significance when
it's broken might be different. But yeah, so I think one at
least simple answer to your point is that when you even if
you did it in two stages, it would still have the טומאה
tumah but I don't know if we'd still call it an oven.
All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says, but now back to
our point. The גמרא Gemara says like this, אבנותיו. Abnotav. טעמא
דאיכא שיעורא דארבע. Taama de'ika shiura d'arba.
So here it sounds that both the חכמים Chachamim and רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir agree that it's only an oven, a normal oven, if
it has four טפחים. tfachim. הלא כשיעורא דארבע טהור. Halo k'shiura d'arba
tahor.
And the חכמים Chachamim are saying here pretty much agree with רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, less than four טפחים tfachim is טהור. tahor. So
why in the previous משנה Mishna did you have to break it
into three parts, if here in this משנה Mishna they agree to
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that less than four is enough? So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמרי התם דצלקי מצלק. Amri hatam d'tzalkei mitzlak.
There where it has to be broken into three and less than
four is not enough is when you cut it widthwise. הכא דעבדי
גיסטרא. Hacha d'avdei gistera.
Here you're cutting it lengthwise. I have to tell you, right,
by right, by cutting a corpse lengthwise, an animal carcass. Anyway,
the גמרא Gemara says, but I have to tell you I don't
understand this cause I don't use these ovens but to me the
opposite makes sense. It's saying if you cut it widthwise, so if
you think if you cut it widthwise, it's more usable, you got
the bottom that's totally functional. There it says for the חכמים Chachamim
less than four oh wait, that oh that does work. I'm sorry.
Okay, so it does work. Okay, so there right, right, so it
does make sense. Okay. So when you cut it widthwise, there the
חכמים Chachamim are saying that less than four is not sufficient. That's
why they don't agree with רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Less than four
is not sufficient. You have to break it into three because it's
still functional if you're cutting it widthwise. If however you're cutting it
lengthwise, what type of function can you do with it? So there
they agree with רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that once it is smaller
than four טפחים, tfachim, of course then I guess you'd have to
measure the four טפחים tfachim the width of the four טפחים. tfachim.
It's a little funny because normally the four טפחים tfachim you think
of measuring as the height. I don't know, anyway there they agree
with רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir because that's less functional that as soon
as it's less than four טפחים, tfachim, you are okay. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara goes on
to back to your point, meaning if it's not usable for the
purpose for which it was designed, even if it's usable for some
other purpose, like you said to keep apples...
oh no, wait a minute, now I understand
wait a minute... now I remember why why it doesn't make sense
because I just reinterpreted so it would make sense, but רשי Rashi
says, רשי Rashi says that the opposite. רשי Rashi says that when
it is widthwise, there they agree that less than four is enough.
But when it's lengthwise, then they need it to be broken more,
they need it to be broken into thirds, less than four's not
enough. So that I don't understand, because if it's widthwise you would
think that the oven is more functional. But the way רשי Rashi
is reading it, התם hatam over there, the new ברייתא Braita we
introduced, when it's less than four, there the חכמים Chachamim agree that
that's enough. But lengthwise, oh that's not enough, then you have to
do even more, then you have to break it into thirds. So
I really don't understand why that would be true.
Yeah, you're saying that either potentially you could use for something else
like let's say to store apples as long as it's not used
for the purpose it was designed then...
right, although again, that's a lot of what מסכת כלים Masechet Keilim
is about, is about how much similar to the original function and
so on does it have to do. Okay. אמר רב שיעורא ברובא.
Amar Rav shiura b'ruba. So again, according to רשי Rashi the חכמים
Chachamim agree to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that less than four's enough,
but for some reason the reason it's easier for for this to
make it טהור tahor when it is being broken widthwise as opposed
to lengthwise, which if somebody has an explanation I would be more
than happy to hear it. אמר מר שיעורא ברובא. Amar mar shiura
b'ruba. So now we're back to this state, now we're back to
the ברייתא Braita we just quoted. The remnant goes by רוב. rov.
So the גמרא Gemara says רובא דטפח למאי חזי? Ruba d'tefach l'mai
chazi? Or הוי havei or חזי. chazi. What can you use this
tiny oven that started as a טפח? tefach? What do you mean,
even if there's still a majority it's still a vessel? What can
you do with something that's just the majority of a טפח? tefach?
It's completely not usable. So אמר אביי שיורי גדול ברובא. Amar Abaye
shiyurei gadol b'ruba. No, when it says the remnant goes by majority,
that's going back to the original statement. The original statement when we
were talking about a large oven. So a large oven רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir said was four טפחים, tfachim, the חכמים Chachamim say a
large oven when you break it it's enough that it's less than
the majority. So the גמרא Gemara says, so now we're back to
a problem. והאמרי רבנן ארבע. Veha'amri rabanan arba.
This is the משנה Mishna where the rabbis agreed to רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir that four was enough. And now we're reinterpreting the rabbis'
statement to say that you need to do the majority, it goes
by majority, not by four. So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא.
lo kashya. הא בתנורא בר תשעה הא בתנורא בר שבע. Ha b'tanura
bar tishah ha b'tanura bar shivah. The question is is whether after
you've done the majority, is it bigger than four or less than
four? So the way... The way this is being read is either
is enough with this oven that's being broken width-wise, which for whatever
reason it's easier to have it considered broken, the rabbis are lenient.
They say either less than four or less than the majority. So
if the oven is nine טפחים tefachim big, then they're going to
say, I'm sorry, if the oven is seven טפחים tefachim big, then
they're going to say you don't have to do less than the
majority, it's enough to do less than four. If it's nine טפחים
tefachim big, they're going to say you don't have to do less
than four, it's enough to do make it small, break away the
majority. Okay, so here the rabbis are being lenient, allow either the
majority or four. רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir always insists on four. This
is in this special case of an oven that's easier to consider
broken because you're breaking it width-wise rather than length-wise. All right. Moving
on. That was the oven. The whole reason we brought in the
oven case was to work with ריש לקיש Reish Lakish who said
that when you're breaking a vessel or a cloth, a garment to
make it טהור, tahor, if it's strong material, it's harder to make
it considered טהור. tahor. If it's leather, it's harder, you have to
do it completely. And we asked from this case of an oven
that it sounds like you don't have to do it completely and
we reframed the cases so that according to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
that all to prevent it from becoming טמא, tamei, but once it's
טמא tamei you do have to break it completely. One last thing,
one last take on this whole ריש לקיש Reish Lakish position and
then we will move on to the next משנה. mishnah. לשון אחר,
Lashon acher, another way of this whole debate. אמרי לה, Amri lah,
it was said, אמר רב הונא משום רבי ישמעאל בר רבי יוסי,
Amar Rav Huna mishum Rabbi Yishmael bar Rabbi Yose, אף אפילו שייר
בה כדי מעפורת. af afillu shiyer bah kedei ma'aforet. So that was
how it started yesterday, that if you have left in the cloth
enough for like a wrap,
then it's not טהור tahor even if you've torn the majority of
the garment. אמר ריש לקיש לא שנו אלא טלית, Amar Reish Lakish
lo shanu ela tallit, that's and this is what we've been focusing
on, it's only like a cloth, אבל עור, aval or, if it's
leather, חשיב. chashiv. Now as opposed to the word חלים, chalim, it
is strong, which led to all those questions about pottery that's strong
and other materials that're strong. Here you're saying no, leather, a leather
garment is more important, so it's not considered like something you would
throw out, it's not considered to have lost its identity even with
a big tear until you tear it completely. So איתיביה רבי יוחנן
לריש לקיש, eitvei Rabbi Yochanan le-Reish Lakish, עור טמא מדרס חישב עליו
לרצועות ובסנדלים, or tamei midras chishav alav le-retzu'ot u-vesandalim, so here and
here there was just one question raised. If you have leather that
became that was used as a mat and it became טמא tamei
because let's say a זב zav sat on it,
כיון שנתן בו איזמל טהור, ke-she-natan bo izmel tahor, as soon as
you apply your awl, you start to cut it, you made it
טהור. tahor. So דברי רבי יהודה, divrei Rabbi Yehuda, that's what רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, וחכמים אומרים עד שימעיטנו מחמשה טפחים, va-chachamim omrim
ad she-yamitenu mi-chamishah tefachim,
that you have to make it smaller than five טפחים. tefachim. And
again, כי ממעיט מהטהור, ki memat mi-ha-tahor, once you get it less
than five טפחים tefachim it is טהור. tahor. And why is that
true according to you, leather which is important, you're saying you have
to completely break fully? So here how come five טפחים tefachim is
sufficient, less than five טפחים tefachim makes it טהור? tahor? אמאי לימא
חשיב, amai laima chashiv, why not say it's important? So במאי חכמים
עסקינן, be-mai chachamim askinan,
what do we talking about? דקא בעי ליה למושב זב, de-ka ba'ei
lei le-moshav zav, some have a גרסא girsa of למכבזג, le-michbeizag,
nobody knows what that word means. Anyway, the point is here you
have a very specific intent that you're going to use it for,
and therefore as soon as because you want to apply it to
a very narrow use, once you decide to change its identity, that's
enough to make it considered no longer a garment. But a normal
piece of leather which you don't have such a narrow use defined
for it would retain its identity because of the importance of leather
until you completely rend it. Fine. That is the end of that,
which was a very big digression from I even forgot what our
משנה mishnah was talking about. Our משנה mishnah was talking about flaying
the skin off of the meat and when is it still considered
connected or not, which led to this loose analogy of rending a
garment, rending leather, when is the thing still considered to be one
unit and connected or not. Let's take a look now at the
next משנה. mishnah. Actually this next משנה mishnah brings us back to
a משנה mishnah in an earlier משנה. mishnah. עור שיש עליו כזית
בשר, Or she-yesh alav ke-zayit basar,
a piece of skin has on it a כזית kezayit of meat
of let's say a נבילה. neveilah. הנוגע בציב היוצא ממנה, Ha-noge'a ba-tziv
ha-yotzei mimena, if you touch a little strand of meat that is
connected, that is trailing but it's connected, או בשערה שכנגדו, o be-sa'arah
she-kenegdo, you touch a hair on the side of the skin, טמא,
tamei, that communicates טומאה. tum'ah. So this is the idea again of
the skin and even a hair being considered a שומר. shomer. Fine.
That was an idea we've already had. Now. היו עליו שני חצי
זיתים, Hayu alav shenei chatzei zeitim,
there is on this piece of skin two half זיתים. zeitim. מטמא
במשא ולא במגע דברי רבי ישמעאל. Metamei be-massa ve-lo be-maga divrei Rabbi
Yishmael. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says you're טמא tamei if you carry
it because this is נבילה neveilah you're טמא tamei even without touching
by carrying, but you're not טמא tamei if you touch. Why? Because
that's considered two separate acts of touching. Okay, and if you touch
one with one finger and one with the other finger, it's two
acts of touching, and therefore to be טמא tamei you have to
touch the minimum size with one act. When you carry it, you're
carrying a כזית, kezayit, but when you're touching it, you're doing two
acts of touching, presumably we're talking not in a case where they're
right next to each other and you're touching them as one, but
and since it's two acts of touching, therefore they don't combine. That's
what רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael says.
רבי עקיבא אומר לא במגע ולא במשא. Rabbi Akiva omer lo bamaga
velo bamassa. It's not טמא tamei either with touching or with carrying.
Why not with carrying? We'll see in a minute.
ומודה רבי עקיבא בשני חצי זיתים שחבזן בקיסם והסיטן שהוא טמא. Umodeh
Rabbi Akiva bishnei chatzei zeitim shechavzan bekisom vehisitan shehu tamei. He would
agree that if you had another scenario like two חצי זיתים chatzei
zeitim that were on a קיסם kisom toothpick and you carried it
without touching it, you would be טמא. tamei. So for רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva normally agrees you're טמא tamei by carrying two חצי זיתים.
chatzei zeitim. Why does he not agree that you're טמא tamei by
carrying these two חצי זיתים chatzei zeitim on a piece of עור
or leather? So ומפני מה רבי עקיבא מטהר בעור? Umipnei mah Rabbi
Akiva metaher ba’or?
Very nice משנה mishna sort of actually spelling out like the exact
issues. Why therefore by the leather does he say you're טהור? tahor?
Why is it different? מפני שהעור מבטלן. Mipnei sheha'or mevatlan. Not because
you're not טמא tamei for carrying two חצי זיתים, chatzei zeitim, but
because when it's on leather, the leather is more significant than the
meat. If it's not a full כזית, kezayit, then then it can't
retain its significance vis-a-vis the leather. So the leather negates the significance
of a half of a זית, zayit, and two חצי זיתים, chatzei
zeitim, if it's not combined as a כזית. kezayit. And that's why.
But generally if you carry two חצי זיתים, chatzei zeitim, you would
be טמא tamei for רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר עולא אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Ulla amar
Rabbi Yochanan, said עולא Ulla אמר רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan לא
שנו אלא פליטתו חיה. lo shanu ela peletato chaya.
Remember this? So it only this is only true that the חצי
זית chatzi zayit has some significance, even according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi
Ishmael, if an animal tore it away. אבל פליטתו סכין בטיל, Aval
peletato sakin batil, if when you were flaying it, the have these
חצי זיתים chatzei zeitim were left on the skin, since it came
through your action, it's like you sort of discarded it, בטיל. batil.
Then even רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael would agree that it is negated
to the leather if it's חצי זיתים. chatzei zeitim. אמר ליה רב
נחמן לעולא, Amar lei Rav Nachman le’Ulla, said רב
נחמן Rav Nachman to עולא, Ulla, אמר רבי יוחנן אפילו כטרטא? Amar
Rabbi Yochanan afilu ketarta? Did רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say that if
you're cutting it away by your, you know, by flaying it, it's
בטיל batil to the skin, even if it's the size of a
טרטא, tarta, which is like a very big size? רש"י Rashi says
it's a quarter of a קב, kav, like like even like, you
know, even a pound, even a, you know, of meat
would be negated to the leather? אמר ליה אין, Amar lei in,
yes. ואפילו כנפיא? Ve'afilu kenafya? Even if it's the size of a
כנפיא, kenafya, like think about a big sieve that you use for,
you know, sifting out flour. Even if it's that much meat just
because it came off with your knife, would he say it's negated
to the leather? אמר ליה אין, Amar lei in, yes. אמר ליה
חי אלוקים אם אמר לי רבי יוחנן מפומיה לא צייתינא ליה, Amar
lei Hai Elokim im amar li Rabbi Yochanan mipumei lo tzitina lei,
said in God's name, if I had heard that straight from רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan's mouth,
I wouldn't listen to it. That's absurd. Even if it comes through
your cutting of the knife, once it's a certain size, it's not
בטיל. batil. And again, you could say less than a כזית, kezayit,
that's the case of the משנה. mishna. Less than a כזית kezayit
is בטיל. batil. But you know, but maybe once it's a כזית,
kezayit, it seems to be the argument even if it comes through
flaying, it still retains its significance. Now we're going to have a
little funny story about about this, let's take a look. כי סליק
רבי אושעיא, Ki salik Rabbi Oshia, when רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshia went
up to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אשכחיה לרבי אמי, ashkachei leRabbi Ammi,
he saw רבי אמי, Rabbi Ammi, he found רבי אמי. Rabbi Ammi.
אמר ליה שמעתא קמיה, Amar lei shemata kammai, he said this discussion
in front of רבי אמי Rabbi Ammi and this back and forth
and then about how, you know, what's his name? How רב נחמן
Rav Nachman didn't want to accept this position of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yochanan.
הכי אמר עולא והכי אהדר ליה רב נחמן. Hachi amar Ulla vehachi
hadar lei Rav Nachman. He said to him, this is what עולא
Ulla said, this is what רב נחמן Rav Nachman said back to
him. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רבי אמי Rabbi Ammi was a
little bit offended. He says ומשום דרב נחמן חתניה דבי נשיאה הוא
מזלזל בשמעתא דרבי יוחנן? Umishum deRav Nachman chasnei devei nesia hu mezalzel
bishmata deRabbi Yochanan? Just because רב נחמן Rav Nachman is the son-in-law
of the from the house of the נשיא, Nasi, מזלזל בשמעתא דרבי
יוחנן? mezalzel bishmata deRabbi Yochanan? He he a חוצפה, chutzpah, you know,
you think because you're related to the נשיא Nasi you can go
ahead and say such a statement? Ah, I wouldn't even accept it
even if I had it straight from יוחנן. Yochanan. You know, so
he was a little offended at the at how emphatic and how
dismissive, I should say, רב נחמן Rav Nachman was. Interesting also how
he understood why רב נחמן Rav Nachman might have felt that he
had a that he had a right to be dismissive. Anyway, so
זימנין zimnin okay now זימנין zimnin another time, but the story isn't
over, okay? זימנין zimnin another time אשכחיה דיתיב. ashkachei deyativ. So who
was it? רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshia found רבי אמי Rabbi Ammi that
was sitting. וקאמר לה אסיפא. Vekamar lah aseifa. And he said over
this issue on the end of the משנה. mishna. היה עליו שני
חצי זיתים מטמאין במשא ולא במגע דברי רבי ישמעאל רבי עקיבא אומר
לא במגע ולא במשא. Haya alav shnei chatzei zeitim mitamin bamassa velo
bamaga divrei Rabbi Ishmael Rabbi Akiva omer lo bamaga velo bamassa. So
he רבי אושעיא, Rabbi Oshia, right, said was saying this thing, right,
so they're debating if it's two חצי זיתים. chatzei zeitim. ואמר רבי
יוחנן לא שנו אלא פליטתו חיה אבל פליטתו סכין בטיל. Ve'amar Rabbi
Yochanan lo shanu ela peletato chaya aval peletato sakin batil. So actually,
I unfortunately conflate
unintentionally conflated the end of the story with the beginning. So the
beginning of the משנה mishna said, right, that if there's a כזית
kezayit of meat, it's a problem. And there, so if you say
this idea that the distinction between an animal and the knife and
you say, oh, but if it's a knife it's different, then you're
saying if it's a knife, it's not a problem, even a כזית.
kezayit. And then the question was, so how big? You know, even
the size of a sieve? But now רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshia is
telling over this statement of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan on the second
part of the משנה, mishna, where רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael says a
half of a כזית kezayit *kazayit* is still an issue, two half
כזיתים *kezaysim*, and on that רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* is saying, oh,
but if it came by the knife, even רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
*Rabbi Yishmael* would agree. So that context makes it clear that he's
only saying that by the knife it's not significant if it's small,
if it's less than half of a כזית *kazayit*. But if it's
a כזית *kazayit*, it certainly even with the knife it would retain
its significance. So on this, אמר ליה רבי אמי לרבי יוחנן *Amar
lei Rabbi Ami leRabbi Yochanan*, לא שנו אלא פליטת אוכלין *lo shanu
ela pleitas ochlin*, פליטת סכין בתר כולי *pleitas sakin batar kulei*. אמר
ליה *Amar lei*, so here, who was it? I'm forgetting the players
here. So Rabbi, so this was what רבי אמי *Rabbi Ami* was
saying. No, no, רבי אמי *Rabbi Ami* was teaching the רבי יוחנן
*Rabbi Yochanan* on the end of the משנה Mishnah *mishna*, where it
made sense. So רבי אושעיא *Rabbi Oshia* said to רבי אמי *Rabbi
Ami*, who was the reporter of the earlier debate, מר אסיפא מתני
לה *Mar aseifa masni lah*? Oh, that's interesting. You're teaching רבי יוחנן's
*Rabbi Yochanan's* statement on the end of the משנה Mishnah *mishna*. That
makes a lot more sense. Now it's limited to under a כזית
*kazayit*. אמר ליה *Amar lei*, is that how you teach it? אמר
ליה אין *Amar lei in*. He said yes. ואלא עולא Ulla. ארישא
אמני להו *Ve'ela Ulla areisha amnei lehu*? And then he said, one
minute. Do you mean... so now רבי אושעיא *Rabbi Oshia* is realizing
what the first story was. So now רבי אושעיא *Rabbi Oshia* is
saying, sorry, I got not רבי אושעיא *Rabbi Oshia*, who was the
one? רבי אמי *Rabbi Ami*. רבי אמי *Rabbi Ami* is realizing. So
רבי אמי *Rabbi Ami* is saying, one minute. ואלא עולא Ulla ארישא
אמני להו *Ve'ela Ulla areisha amnei lehu*? You mean to tell me
when עולא Ulla *Ulla* told you this רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, he
told it to you on the רישא *reisha* of the משנה *mishna*?
He told it to you bigger than a כזית *kazayit*? Even on
a כזית *kazayit* that the knife would, you know, make it negated?
אמר ליה אין *Amar lei in*. Yes, that was the point. So
אמר ליה *Amar lei*, so now רבי אמי *Rabbi Ami* said, האלקים
*HaElokim*, in God's name, אי אמרה לי יהושע בן נון משמיה לא
צייתנא ליה *i amrah li Yehoshua bin Nun mishmei lo tzyisnah lei*.
Even if I heard this from the mouth of יהושע בן נון
*Yehoshua bin Nun*, I wouldn't accept it. ואתון אמריתו הכי *Ve'atun amrisu
hachi*? Yes. So
anyway, so the same רבי אמי *Rabbi Ami* that took offense at
how, you know, dismissive. Now that he understood how absurd the statement
really was. He thought the whole thing was on the end of
the משנה *mishna*, it was less than a כזית *kazayit*. Now that
he understood how absurd it was, he's making even a more a
stronger statement about I wouldn't have even accepted it from יהושע בן
נון *Yehoshua bin Nun*. Okay. So now, how do you defend this
statement if it's even bigger than a כזית *kazayit*? It is so
absurd, right? It should retain its identity. כי אתא רבין וכל נחותי
ימא *Ki ata Ravin vechol nechusei yama*, when רבין *Ravin* came and
all those that sort of came from the sea, it's an interesting
phrase, אמרו ארישא *amru areisha*. They said like this, it goes even
on the beginning of the משנה *mishna*, that if it came from
a knife even bigger than a כזית *kazayit*, it's negated. ואלא קשיא
*Ve'ela kashya*, so what about all of our, you know, being astounded
by it? כדאמר רב פפא במרודד *Kedamar Rav Pappa bimrudad*, like רב
פפא *Rav Pappa* would say later in today's דף *daf*, when it
is thinned out. הכא נמי במרודד *Hacha nami bimrudad*, it's thinned out.
You could have more than a כזית *kazayit*, but it's not like
a nice chunk of a כזית *kazayit*. What you have is you
have a כזית *kazayit* like that's the size of a micron high.
You know what I mean? Just like, you know, very, very, you
know, and it's thin. Imagine like my my, my example of like
peeling cucumbers, right? So imagine you do a long peel of a
cucumber and it's all of the little bit of meat that you
sort of that is still on the peel. If you put it
together, could be like a lot of cucumber. But who the heck
is going to try to scrape off all of that? So there,
no matter how much it is, if it's very, very thin, it
can lose its significance to the leather. So that makes a lot
more sense. Okay. היו עליו *hayu alav*, moving on.
Would it also be if it's divided into more than just two
pieces?
No, here we're talking about if it's one piece, if it's going
on the רישא *reisha*. The רישא *reisha* of the statement is that
when it came from the knife, then even if it's bigger than
even if one piece and it's bigger than a כזית *kazayit*, it
loses its significance. How could that be? If it's one continuous piece
that's super thin. Okay.
Now we're talking about just two half...
that's the second part of the משנה *mishna*.
Right, but if it's four quarters, would that be the same?
That would be the same, yeah. Okay, but now, so now moving
on to the second part of the משנה *mishna* about two חצי
זיתים chatzei zeitim, *chatzi zeisim*, where רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael*
says you're carrying both of them and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi
Akiva* says, well, I agree normally if you carry two חצי זיתים
chatzei zeitim *chatzi zeisim*, but here the skin negates, okay, makes it
considered not present. So אמר בר פדא Bar Padda, *Amar Bar Pada*,
לא שנו אלא מאחורה *lo shanu ela me'achora*. When is it that
we say
that if you touch these חצי זיתים chatzei zeitim *chatzi zeisim*, you're
לא טמא tamei *lo tamei*? If you touch them from behind, you
touch them on the skin side. So then the skin would not
be considered a שומר *shomer* to a half of a כזית *kazayit*.
That's why. אבל מלפניה *Aval milfaneha*, if you touch them in the
front, you actually touch the meat itself, יש נוגע וחוזר ונוגע *yesh
nogei vechozer venogei*. רבי *Rabbi* actually what we took for granted in
the משנה *mishna* is not true. If you do two acts of
touching, you would become טמא tamei *tamei* and you'd combine them, which
is a strange idea. ורבי יוחנן אמר *Verabbi Yochanan amar*, רבי יוחנן
*Rabbi Yochanan* says, no, אין נוגע וחוזר ונוגע *ein nogei vechozer venogei*.
No, it's not true. If you touch it two separate acts, you
are not טמא tamei *tamei*. Everybody agrees to that. The only issue
in the משנה *mishna* was whether you carried them, because that's one
act of carrying. ורבי יוחנן לטעמיה *Verabbi Yochanan leta'amei*. רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* goes according to his reasoning. דאמר רבי יוחנן *De'amar Rabbi Yochanan*,
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael, ורבי דוסא בן הרכינס אמרו דבר אחד *Rabbi
Yishmael veRabbi Dosa ben Hurkinas amru davar echad*. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael.
*Rabbi Yishmael* and רבי דוסא בן הרכינס *Rabbi Dosa ben Hurkinas* said
the same thing, or essentially the same thing. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael?
*Rabbi Yishmael*, הא דאמרן *ha de'amran*, what we said by רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael*, that if you touch two separate חצי זיתים
zeisim *chatzi zeisim* you're not טמא tamei *tamei*, it doesn't combine. ורבי
דוסא בן הרכינס דתנן *VeRabbi Dosa ben Hurkinas detnan*, an analogous case
not by touching but by being in an אהל *ohel*, under a
roof for the טומאה *tumah* of a מת *meis*.
anything that causes טומאה *tumah* in an אוהל ohel *ohel*, like a
כזית *kezayit* from a corpse that was split into half, so you
have two half כזיתים *kezaysim* that are now—where am I? שנחלקו והכניסן
לתוך הבית *shenechleku vehichnisan letoch habayit*,
you brought them into the house, so you have two separate half
כזיתים *kezaysim* in a house. רבי דוסא בן הרכינס מטהר וחכמים מטמאים
*Rabbi Dosa ben Harkinas metaher vechachamim metamin*. רבי דוסא בן הרכינס *Rabbi
Dosa ben Harkinas* says it's טהור tahor *tahor* and the חכמים *chachamim*
say it's טמא tamei *tamei*. So, לאו אמר רבי דוסא בן הרכינס
התם אין מאהיל וחוזר ומאהיל *lav amar Rabbi Dosa ben Harkinas hatam
ein ma'ahil vechozer uma'ahil*? The same way there he says being מאהיל
*ma'ahil*, turning the word of אוהל *ohel* into a verb, being a
canopy over, being a roof over a half of a כזית *kezayit*
and a half of a כזית *kezayit* does not combine if it's
two separate half כזיתים *kezaysim*. הכא נמי אינו נוגע וחוזר ונוגע *hacha
nami ein nogea vechozer venogea*, it's similar to the idea of two
separate acts of touching. Now, תוספות *Tosafot* points out that there's a
big difference because remember in our משנה *Mishnah* everybody agrees that when
you carry two half כזיתים *kezaysim*, it is one act of carrying.
So if I asked you, what is the case of two half
כזיתים *kezaysim* being under a roof more similar to? Touching two half
כזיתים *kezaysim* or carrying? Carrying. It's one act of carrying, one act
of being under a roof as opposed to two acts of touching,
right? So תוספות *Tosafot* says, you know, I don't—it's not really an
analogy. If everybody agreed, why is carrying different than this case of
the roof? So תוספות *Tosafot* actually says that even by carrying, as
we're going to see later, it's only because we have a special
פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. But even if it really was physically one act,
being under the roof, being carried, for those that say you do—you
know, it doesn't count when it's split, it doesn't matter two acts
or one act. Whether it's touching, whether it's being under the roof,
if it's a split כזית *kezayit* it doesn't count. The only exception
according to this approach will be carrying, and it's not really about
two acts versus one act. Even when it's one act, if it's
two half sizes it doesn't count and there's a special exception by
carrying which we will see. So that is the position of רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael*. But now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has
a question. Let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*'s question.
So רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael, *Rabbi Yishmael* says you don't have two
acts of touching and a similar position of רבי דוסא בן הרכינס
*Rabbi Dosa ben Harkinas*, you don't have two acts of being under
a roof or if it's two halves it doesn't count. So now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one minute, מדירבי דוסא בן הרכינס כרבי
ישמעאל *mideRabbi Dosa ben Harkinas keRabbi Yishmael*, now that he's aligned with
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael, *Rabbi Yishmael*, רבנן כרבי עקיבא *Rabbanan keRabbi Akiva*.
If it's really the same debate, although you know you obviously don't
have to say it's identical, then the Rabbis that argue with רבי
דוסא בן הרכינס *Rabbi Dosa ben Harkinas* presumably is the רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva. *Rabbi Akiva* of our משנה *Mishnah*. Now again, that's not
necessarily the case, right? I mean even if—but anyway, that's what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is doing. It's lining everything up. So it's going
to say but one minute, what do the חכמים *Chachamim* say? Two
half כזיתים *kezaysim* under a roof is טמא tamei *tamei*. So if
that's the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* of our משנה *Mishnah*,
then רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva's *Rabbi Akiva* should say that two half
כזיתים *kezaysim* is טמא tamei, *tamei* if you touch them as two
halves or if you carry them as two halves. So why in
our משנה *Mishnah* does he argue and say you're טהור *tahor*? So
the גמרא *Gemara* says, והא רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva טהורי קמטהר *vehaRabbi
Akiva tahorei kametaher*, he says it's טהור *tahor* in our משנה *Mishnah*.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says no, עד כאן לא קמטהר רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva אלא בעור *ad kan lo kametaher Rabbi Akiva ela be'or*.
The only reason רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva's *Rabbi Akiva* says you're טהור
*tahor* in our משנה *Mishnah* is because of this idea that the
leather negates the two half כזיתים *kezaysim*. אבל באלמא *Aval be'alma*, in
general, מטמא *metamei*,
he would agree that even with two halves you are טמא tamei
*tamei*. כדתני סיפא *Kidetani seifa*, which is what the end of the
משנה *Mishnah*
says. ומודה רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva's בשני חצי זיתים zeisim שתחבן בקיצה
והסיטן שהוא טמא tamei *Umodeh Rabbi Akiva beshnei chatzi zeitim shetachavan bekitza
vehisitan shehu tamei*, that he agrees that if you carry two half
חצי זיתים zeisim *chatzi zeitim* on a twig that you are טמא
tamei, *tamei* even if it's two halves. ובפני מה רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva, מטהר בעור *Ubifnei mah Rabbi Akiva metaher be'or*? So why then
when you carry them on the skin does he say you're טהור
*tahor*? מפני שהעור מבטלן *Mifnei sheha'or mevatlan*, because the skin negates them.
So now what are we saying? We're saying like this. We're saying
that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael* holds that if you touch
two halves you're טהור *tahor*. If you're מאהיל *ma'ahil* on two halves
according to a similar position of רבי דוסא בן הרכינס *Rabbi Dosa
ben Harkinas*, you're טהור *tahor*. But if you carry two halves you're
טמא tamei *tamei*, that's a special exception. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva's *Rabbi
Akiva* we're saying, at least if we want to align them, that
even if you touch two halves you're טמא tamei *tamei* and if
you're מאהיל *ma'ahil* on two halves you're טמא tamei *tamei*. And the
only reason he's lenient in the משנה *Mishnah* is because the skin
negates. But in principle, besides the issue of skin, he's actually stricter
than רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael* and would say that even
when it's two halves you're טמא tamei *tamei*.
You have to carry them too.
Certainly carrying two halves as long as you don't have the skin
problem.
Okay, now let's see where the גמרא *Gemara* goes. Carrying them with
skin you'd be—you're טהור *tahor* because the skin negates, not like you
have skin here and the halves here, connected, right, and the skin
negates their significance. Okay, now, מתקיף רבי עוקבא בר חמא *matki Rabbi
Ukva bar Chama*, so רבי עוקבא בר חמא *Rabbi Ukva bar Chama*
asked, בנבלתם *benivlatam*, the ברייתא *Baraita* says quoting the פסוק *pasuk* that
if you touch the נבילה *neveilah* of these dead animals that make
you טמא tamei *tamei*. ולא בעור שיש עליו כשני חצי זיתים zeisim
*Velo be'or sheyesh alav keshnei chatzi zeitim*, not if you touch skin
that has two half חצי זיתים zeisim *chatzi zeitim* on it. This
is we're going to see is רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael? *Rabbi Yishmael*'s
position because that's two touchings. יכול אף במשא *Yakhol af bamasah*? Maybe
even if you carry it this way you're טהור *tahor*? תלמוד לומר
והנושא יטמא *Talmud lomar vehanosei yitma*, and the one who carries is
טמא tamei *tamei*, and therefore since maybe it doesn't... emphasize
בנבלתם, it's hard to understand exactly what part of the פסוק they're
emphasizing, but anyway, that's what רבי ישמעאל says, that by carrying you
are טמא tamei for two halves. דברי רבי ישמעאל. Divrei Rabbi Yishmael.
That's what רבי ישמעאל says.
רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, הנוגע והנושא, hanogea vehanosei, no, he
says look, the verse compares, lines up, it says הנוגע בנבלתם hanogea
binivlatam והנושא את נבלתם. vehanosei et nivlatam. So since it says, it
uses these two verbs, touching and carrying, sort of right side by
side, so what does that tell us? It tells us a new
very important principle. כל שבא לכלל מגע בא לכלל משא. kol sheba
lichlal maga ba lichlal masa. לא בא לכלל מגע לא בא לכלל
משא. lo ba lichlal maga lo ba lichlal masa. Something that you
could become טמא tamei through touching, you become טמא tamei through carrying.
If it's impossible to become טמא tamei through touching, you also can't
become טמא tamei, through carrying. One way of understanding that is carrying
is a type of indirect touching. So therefore, it has to be
able to become טמא tamei, through touching. That's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva's says. He says if you admit to me, you רבי ישמעאל,
that if you touch one half and the other half you're not
טמא, tamei, so it can't become טמא tamei through an act of
touching, it also can't become טמא tamei through an act of carrying.
Okay, so that is רבי עקיבא. So now the גמרא says, ואם
איתא, ve'im ita, but if what you're saying is correct, הרי בא
לכלל מגע מלפניו, harei ba lichlal maga milifanav, meaning you, בר פדא,
Bar Padda at the beginning of this discussion, we're going back, remember
בר פדא Bar Padda. said that actually if you touch the two
halves you are טמא, tamei the only case in the משנה was
when you touch them from behind, but when you actually touch the
meat itself, you would become טמא tamei according to רבי ישמעאל. So
if that's true, what's רבי עקיבא challenging רבי ישמעאל? רבי ישמעאל says
yeah, you can become טמא tamei as long as you touch them
the meat itself, so that's why you can also become טמא tamei
when you carry it. So אמר רבא הכי קאמר. amar Rava hachi
ka'amar. No, here's how, if that's where, if רבי ישמעאל agrees you
could be טמא tamei from touching the meat, here would be רבי
עקיבא's challenge. כל שבא לכלל מגע בכל צד, kol sheba lichlal maga
bechol tzad, if only if you could become טמא tamei by touching
it at any side, even on the skin side, בא לכלל משא,
ba lichlal masa, only then will you become טמא tamei by carrying
it. לא בא לכלל מגע בכל צד, lo ba lichlal maga bechol
tzad, if you can't become טמא tamei by touching it on any
side, then לא בא לכלל משא, lo ba lichlal masa, you cannot
become טמא tamei, by carrying. Although there, the logic is a lot
harder to understand. Why should you need to be able to become
טמא tamei by touching it not on the meat itself in order
to enable you to become טמא tamei through carrying it? Anyway, that's
to defend בר פדא. But the basic important point is we've introduced
a couple of points. Number one is, is that some things according
to רבי ישמעאל, two halves you're not טמא, tamei touching two halves,
presumably once we compare it to being under the roof of two
halves, touching them at the same time with the same finger, touching
two halves not being under the roof of two halves, the only
exception is carrying. And רבי עקיבא says be consistent. If you're going
to say, I might say touching two halves you are טמא, tamei
but if you're going to say touching two halves you're not טמא,
tamei carrying you're only going to be טמא tamei if it could
have made you טמא tamei through touching. Okay, and that's an important
principle, the idea that טומאת משא tumat masa might be based on
the concept of טומאת מגע, tumat maga, carrying based on the concept
of touching.
It's a good point, right?
Well, what do you mean with carrying is?
רבי ישמעאל, רבי עקיבא disagrees.
In practice you're חייב chayav for carrying without touching, but it might
be because it's conceptually a type of indirect touching and it might
need to have the potential of becoming טמא through touching. And we'll
see another example of that in the גמרא. Okay, בעי מיניה רב
אביא סבא מרבה בר בר רב הונא. ba'ei minei Rav Avia Saba
meRabba bar bar Rav Huna. So רב אביא Rav Avia the elder
asked from רבה בר בר רב הונא, Rabba bar bar Rav Huna,
קוליס סתומה, kulis stuma,
here's another nice example of that. You have, remember the קוליס kulis
is like the
thigh bone, it's a very big bone, it has a כזית of
meat in its marrow, okay, but it's totally closed, the bone is
not cracked. So now you're only חייב chayav if you were to
touch the meat, the marrow. So you can't touch the meat, it's
protected by the bone. What if you carried the bone? What if
you lifted up the bone? That's considered carrying, just lifting it, moving
it. Would you be טמא since you can't get to the meat
to touch it? That's this question. Okay, so מהו שתטמא, mahu shetitma,
would it become, would you become טמא if you moved it or
carried it? אית ליה לרבי ישמעאל is lei leRabbi Yishmael כל שבא
לכלל מגע בא לכלל משא, kol sheba lichlal maga ba lichlal masa,
לא בא לכלל מגע לא בא לכלל משא, lo ba lichlal maga
lo ba lichlal masa, does he agree to רבי עקיבא's principle
that you're only טמא for moving if you could be טמא for
touching? והכא היינו טעמא משום דבא לכלל מגע מלפניו, vehacha hainu ta'ama
mishum deba lichlal maga milifanav, and the only reason רבי ישמעאל says
that you're טמא by the חצי זיתים, even though is because there
the reason he said by touching you're not טמא is he meant
touching on the back side, on the skin side, but he actually
would say that you are טמא by touching the meat, and therefore
he really agrees to רבי עקיבא's principle. Maybe רבי ישמעאל says you're
טמא, I agree to this רבי עקיבא, you have to become, you're
only טמא for carrying if you're טמא for touching, and the reason
I say you're חייב, chayav, you're טמא for carrying these two חצי
זיתים is I also say you're טמא for touching the two חצי
זיתים when you touch them directly. The only time I said that
you're טהור is when you touch them from the back side. Is
that how we understand רבי ישמעאל? But he one minute, but he
basically agrees to רבי עקיבא's principle that it has to be able
to become טמא by touching. או דלמא לית ליה, o dilma leis
lei, or maybe he just rejects רבי עקיבא's principle and he says
yes, you're is what רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael* sounds like, you're not
טמא *tamei* for touching, but carrying is a different category and you
are טמא *tamei* for carrying. So that was what this question was
asking.
Let me re-read the question. So the first case, you have this
bone, so there's version A and version B, you know. So everyone
would agree he's טהור *tahor* and the second way only potentially רבי
ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael* would say you're טמא *tamei*.
I'm not sure what you're asking. I'll get back to you in
a minute. So אמר ליה *amar lei*, so that was the question.
The question was you have this bone that you cannot get to
the meat in it, you can't touch it. You can't touch the
meat so you cannot become טמא *tamei* by touching. Can you become
טמא *tamei* by carrying? Does רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael* agree to the
bottom line is does רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael* agree to the principle
of רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* that you're only טמא *tamei* for carrying
if you're טמא *tamei* for touching. That was the question רבי סבא
*Rabbi Sabba* asked, רבי אביא סבא *Rabbi Avia Sabba* asked רב בר
בר חנה *Rav Bar Bar Chuna*. So אמר ליה *amar lei*, so
רב בר בר חנה *Rav Bar Bar Chuna* says to him, עורבא
פרח *orba parach*, oh look, there's a bird flying.
So אמר ליה רבא בריה *amar lei Rava brei*, so רבא *Rava*
his son said to him, one minute, what type of answer was
that? לאו היינו רבי אביא סבא מפומבדיתא *Labaihu Rabbi Avia Sabba miPumbedita*,
isn't this רבי אביא *Rabbi Avia* the elder from פומבדיתא *Pumbedita* דמשבח
לן מר בגוויה *de'mshabach lan mar begavei*, you normally are praising him?
דגברא רבה הוא *de'gavra rabba hu*, what a great תלמיד חכם *talmid
chacham* he is. So what are you doing like changing the subject,
like dismissing his question? So it's like two interesting stories on the
same page. Anyway, so אמר ליה *amar lei*, so he said back
to him, no, it's not about the questioner. אני היום סמכוני באשישות
*Ani hayom samchuni ba'ashishot*. Today I have been like supported in, what's
אשישות *ashishot*? Whatever it is. Anyway, which means the way רש"י *Rashi*
says it means
flasks of wine.
Anyway, it's רש"י *Rashi* says that it means that I'm exhausted. I
just came through from giving a give, a big שבת הגדול *Shabbat
HaGadol* דרשה *drasha*, it was a דרשה *drasha* on the רגל *regel*.
I don't have the head now to be thinking about a קשיא
*kasha* about רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael* or רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, whatever.
Okay, so I was so exhausted, give me a break, you know.
All right, anyway, ובעי מיניה *u'ba'ei minei*, it's like rabbis do this
all the time. You just finished this big lecture, the only thing
you want to do is go home and lie down and everybody
has a hundred questions they want to ask you. Okay, anyway, ובעי
מיניה *u'ba'ei minei*, okay, ובעי מיניה מילתא דבעי טעמא *u'ba'ei minei milta
de'ba'ei ta'ama*, he was asking me something that required me to focus
and think, so I changed the topic. All right, anyway, so we
don't know. So
anyway, so
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* holds of a principle, we have a couple
of interesting principles here. Number one, are you חייב *chayav* by touching
two halves, being an אוהל *ohel* over two halves, you know, is
that considered, are you חייב *chayav*, is that טמא *tamei* or not?
And number two is if you can't become טמא *tamei* through touching,
can you become טמא *tamei* through carrying? רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says
no, only things that you can become טמא *tamei* touching, טמא *tamei*
carrying. It's not clear whether רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael* agrees or doesn't
agree. It sounds like he doesn't agree. It sounds like he says
when you touch the pieces of meat you're טהור *tahor*, but when
you carry them you're טמא *tamei*. But maybe he's saying you're טהור
*tahor* because of the special case, because you touched them on the
skin side. Okay, let's try to get to the משנה *Mishnah*. Now,
אמר עולא *amar Ulla*, so said עולא *Ulla*, שני חצאי זיתים שתחבן
בקיסם *shenei chatzei zeisim she'thavan be'kisa*, so he's basically saying exactly the
case of our משנה *Mishnah*. You take these two halves זיתים *zeisim*
of a נבילה *neveilah* which are where you have a twig going
through them, אפילו מוליך ומביא כל היום כולו טהור *afilu molich u'meivi
kol hayom kulo tahor*. Even if you're bringing back and forth the
whole day, you're טהור *tahor*. Obviously, I mean once you're טהור *tahor*
once, you're טהור *tahor* the whole day. Anyway, מאי טעמא *mai ta'ama*?
It sounds like he's totally disagreeing with our משנה *Mishnah*, at least
with the that said that you are טמא *tamei* in that case.
כתיב *kesiv*, because the verse says והנושא *ve'hanosei*, if you carry, דקרינן
*de'karinan* נושא *nosei*, if you, I mean actually right, it's written without
the vav, we read נושא *nosei*, carry, בעינן נושא והוא דנישא *ba'inan
nosei ve'hu de'nisai*. You need to carry it, but in a way
that it could be sort of carried itself, you know, connected, carried,
sort of one part picks up the other part. Meaning, if it's
two separate halves, since if you were to pick up one half
by itself, not with the twig, the other half wouldn't come along,
they're separate, so therefore you're not חייב *chayav* for carrying. So he
basically says whatever, not the point about you have to be טמא
*tamei* for touching. Whether you're טמא *tamei* for touching the two halves
or not, maybe you are, maybe you're not, my principle isn't that.
My principle is to become טמא *tamei* for carrying, it's a special
דין *din* that it has to be one piece, based on the
word נושא *nosei*, carry, it also means the piece has to carry
itself and have to be one piece. So I, which seems to
be straight against the entire משנה *Mishnah*. So let's see what the
גמרא *Gemara* says. תנן *Tenan*, so we said in our משנה *Mishnah*,
היו עליו שני חצאי זיתים מטמא במשא ולא במגע דברי רבי ישמעאל
*hayu alav shenei chatzei zeisim mitamei be'massa ve'lo be'maga, divrei Rabbi Ishmael*.
So here exactly that case, two halves זיתים *zeisim* on a piece
of leather. So אמאי *amai*? והא לא נישא הוא *ve'ha lo nisai
hu*? רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael* says you're טמא *tamei*. So אמאי *amai*?
והא לא נישא הוא *ve'ha lo nisai hu*? It's not one piece.
אמר רב פפא *Amar Rav Papa*, במרודא *bi'meruda*, that's what we quoted
earlier. Yes, it's a very thin piece of meat spread throughout on
the entire leather. Now of course if that's, if it's, תוספות *Tosafot*
says, but then it's not two halves זיתים *zeisim* anymore. So תוספות
*Tosafot* doesn't understand how these answers are really working. תא שמע *Ta
shema*, we're going to try again.
Look at the bird.
Yeah. מודה רבי עקיבא בשני חצאי זיתים שתחבן בקיסם והסיטן שהוא טמא
*Modeh Rabbi Akiva bi'shenei chatzei zeisim she'thavan be'kisa ve'hisitan she'hu tamei*. Exactly
what you said, two halves זיתים *zeisim* on a twig, you move
it, you're טמא *tamei*. It's exactly against your case and it's exactly
the opposite. אמאי *amai*? והא לא נישא הוא *ve'ha lo nisai hu*?
It's not one piece that moves with itself. הכא נמי *hacha nami*
במרודא *bi'meruda*. We don't literally mean two halves זיתים *zeisim*, they're still
connected by a thin, a thin piece of meat. Again, then why
are we calling them two halves? All right. כתנאי. This is a
debate of תנאים. tannaim. אחד הנוגע ואחד המסיט, echad hanogei'ah v'echad hamesit,
רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, whether you touch these two זיתים
or move them, רבי אליעזר אומר אף הנושא, Rabbi Eliezer omer af
hanosei, even if you carry them. The גמרא says, what do you
mean? Moving is the same halakhic category as carrying. Okay. אטו נושא
לאו מסיט הוא? atu nosei lav mesit hu? Carrying is moving, it's
the same halakhic category. אלא לאו הכי קאמר. ela lav hachi ka'amar.
Let's read this מחלוקת תנאים machlokes tannaim to be this position of
עולא. אחד הנוגע ואחד המסיט בלא ניסת, echad hanogei'ah v'echad hamesit belo
nisa, whether you touched or carried two half זיתים even if they
are really separate, one doesn't move with the other, ואתא רבי אליעזר
למימרא והוא דניסת. v'asa Rabbi Eliezer l'meimra v'hu d'nisa. No, it's not
true. Only if those two half זיתים are half זיתים are connected
so that one will move with the other. And מאי אף? mai
af? What does it mean even? Even sounds like you're being expanding
the case as instead of limiting it. אימא והוא דניסת. eima v'hu
d'nisa. So reread it to say only if, only if. So again,
very, very strange. עולא says a position which is against the entire
משנה and the גמרא goes out of its way to somehow try
to say it's possible to support it or possible not to contradict
it and maybe that's what's going on with this debate. But anyway,
beyond עולא's point, the more interesting thing is that touching two half
זיתים or being an אוהל over two halves is one thing that's
debated, and the other thing that's debated is can you be טמא
for carrying if you can't be טמא for touching.